<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
Data to be used by Sand Paper's help box
-->


<root>
    <group name="textures">
        <control name="texturesTab">
            <title>The textures tab</title>
            <text>The tab for importing textures.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="texturesColored">
            <title>The colored textures box</title>
            <text>Contains all of the imported textures that have color./n/n
            These textures can be used as shift, diffuse, displacement, bump or 
            specular maps for the terrain or a population.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="texturesColoredAdd">
            <title>The add texture button for colored textures</title>
            <text>Import a texture to be used as a colored map./n/nColored maps
            can be used as shift, diffuse, displacement, bump or specular maps 
            for the terrain or a population.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="texturesGrayscale">
            <title>The grayscale textures box</title>
            <text>Contains all of the imported textures that have no color./n/n
            These textures can be used as placement, width or height maps for a 
            population.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="texturesGrayscaleAdd">
            <title>The add texture button for colorless textures</title>
            <text>Import a texture to be used as a colorless map./n/nColorless 
            maps can be used as placement, width or height maps for a 
            population.</text>
        </control>
    </group>
    
    <group name="terrain">
        <control name="terrainTab">
            <title>The terrain tab</title>
            <text>The tab for adjusting the terrain./n/nThe terrain is the base 
            flat surface that is used with making the 3D surface.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="terrainVertexWidth">
            <title>The width of the terrain</title>
            <text>The number of vertices that make up the width of the terrain. 
            Each vertex is a point in the terrain that is raised or lowered./n/n
            Increasing the number will make the terrain wider, smoother and 
            more detailed, but it is more demanding on your computer. 
            Decreasing the number will do the opposite./n/nIt is best to use a
            low number while working with the terrain and populations, then use 
            a high number just before creating an image render./n/nBe careful
            with using high numbers on older computers. If you are unsure, it 
            is best to slowly increase the number (50 or 100 at a time) and see 
            how the computer handles it.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="terrainVertexDepth">
            <title>The depth of the terrain</title>
            <text>The number of vertices that make up the depth of the terrain. 
            Each vertex is a point in the terrain that is raised or lowered./n/n
            Increasing the number will make the terrain longer, smoother and 
            more detailed, but it is more demanding on your computer. 
            Decreasing the number will do the opposite./n/nIt is best to use a
            low number while working with the terrain and populations, then use 
            a high number just before creating an image render./n/nBe careful
            with using high numbers on older computers. If you are unsure, it 
            is best to slowly increase the number (50 or 100 at a time) and see 
            how the computer handles it.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="terrainDisplacement">
            <title>The displacement map that the terrain uses</title>
            <text>Choose a color texture that has been imported to use as a 
            displacement map. A displacement map defines the shape of the 
            terrain./n/nHow a certain part of the terrain is shifted is
            dependant on the color of the corresponding part of the map./nMore 
            red will shift left. Less red will shift right./nMore green will 
            shift up. Less green will shift down./nMore blue will shift 
            forward. Less blue will shift backward./n/nIt is best for beginners 
            to create these maps by beginning with an image with a black 
            background and painting using only green at different opacities to 
            raise certain areas by certain amounts. More advanced users may 
            want to begin with a gray (R:127, G:127, B:127) background and then 
            add or remove red, green or blue at different areas of the map to 
            the desired shape.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="terrainStrength">
            <title>The control for setting how much the terrain should be 
            displaced</title>
            <text>A higher value will make the displacement more extreme, 
            moving the vertices out more. A lower value will make it less 
            noticeable, keeping the vertices closer in.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="terrainDiffuse">
            <title>The diffuse map that the terrain uses</title>
            <text>Choose a color texture that has been imported to use as a 
            diffuse map. A diffuse map is the actual appearance of the terrain.
            /n/nA diffuse map can be thought of as being similar to wrapping
            paper. It does not change the shape of the terrain at all, but it 
            determines the color and patterns covering the terrain.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="terrainBump">
            <title>The bump map that the terrain uses</title>
            <text>Choose a color texture that has been imported to use as a 
            bump map. A bump map defines the tiny details of the shape of the 
            terrain./n/nBump maps technically do not change the shape of the 
            terrain at all, but rather give the allusion of the shape changing 
            slightly. It is useful for creating details on the surface such as 
            bumps and cracks./n/nSand Paper uses a type of colored bump map
            known as a normal map. These maps are difficult to create by hand,
            however, there are applications (such as GIMP) that are capable of 
            applying a filter on the diffuse map to generate a normal map that 
            can be used here.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="terrainSpecular">
            <title>The specular map that the terrain uses</title>
            <text>Choose a color texture that has been imported to use as a 
            specular map. A specular map determines how much light the terrain
            should reflect./n/nThe darker parts of the specular map will make 
            the corresponding part of the terrain to be less reflective, and 
            lighter areas will be more reflective./n/nA specular map is usually 
            created from a grayscale version of the diffuse or bump map. After 
            darkening and lightening different parts of the image, tints of 
            color can be added to different areas of the map to add a tint of 
            color to the reflection.</text>
        </control>
    </group>
    
    <group name="populations">
        <control name="populationsTab">
            <title>The populations tab</title>
            <text>This tab is used for creating and modifying populations. In
            Sand Paper, populations are a group of planes that are spread 
            across the surface of the terrain. By default, these planes always 
            face the camera to help convey the allusion that they are 3D 
            objects when a rendered image is created./n/nPopulations are useful 
            for creating trees, grass, hair, people in a crowd or other things 
            that may stand up from the terrain's surface./n/nLarge populations
            may be demanding on your PC (especially when the terrain has high 
            vertex dimensions.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="populationsChosen">
            <title>The population selection box</title>
            <text>Select a population to edit in this box. Any changes made to 
            the settings on this tab will apply only to the population selected 
            in this box.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="populationsNew">
            <title>The new population button</title>
            <text>Creates a new population./n/nYou will get to give the 
            population a name. The population will then be selectable in the 
            combo box directly above this button.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="populationsGenerate">
            <title>The button for recreating the population</title>
            <text>Generates the population again./n/nSince random numbers are 
            used when calculating the population's placement and displacement, 
            the population will most-likely have a slightly different 
            appearance.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="populationsDelete">
            <title>The population deletion button</title>
            <text>Deletes the population that is currently selected.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="populationsPlacement">
            <title>The placement map that the selected population uses</title>
            <text>Choose a grayscale texture that has been imported to use as a 
            placement map. A placement map determines where on the terrain the 
            population should exist./n/nA black area on the map will cover the 
            corresponding area on the terrain with the population. A white area 
            on the map will make the corresponding area on the terrain void of 
            the population. A gray area will be partially populated depending 
            on how light or dark the area is./n/nUsing a dark placement map can 
            usually be very demanding on the PC.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="populationsShift">
            <title>The shift map that the selected population uses</title>
            <text>Choose a colored texture that has been imported to use as a 
            shift map. A shift map determines how much the population should be 
            moved in various areas./n/nThe amount of red that a certain area of
            the map has will shift the population in the coresponding area on 
            the terrain either left or right./nThe green amount will shift the 
            population in that area up or down./nThe blue amount will shift
            forward or back</text>
        </control>
        <control name="populationsWidth">
            <title>The map that determines the width of the selected 
            population</title>
            <text>Choose a grayscale texture that has been imported to use as a 
            width map. A width map determines how much space should be between 
            each vertex horizontally./n/nThe darker a part of the map is, the
            skinnier the population will be in the corresponding area on the
            terrain. The lighter it is, the wider the population will be in the 
            corresponding area./n/nUnlike changing the vertex dimensions, this 
            map adjusts the width without lowering or raising the population's 
            quality. In other words, this map changes the population's width 
            without affecting the computer's performance.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="populationsHeight">
            <title>The map that determines the height of the selected
            population</title>
            <text>Choose a grayscale texture that has been imported to use as a 
            map for the population's height. This map determines how much space 
            should exist between each vertex vertically./n/nThe darker a part 
            of the map is, the shorter the population will be in the 
            corresponding area on the terrain. The lighter it is, the taller 
            the population will be in the corresponding area./n/nUnlike 
            changing the vertex dimensions, this map adjusts the height without 
            lowering or raising the population's quality. In other words, this 
            map changes the population's height without affecting the 
            computer's performance.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="populationsVertexWidth">
            <title>How many vertices should make up the width of each 
            individual object</title>
            <text>Choose how many vertices should exist in each row of vertices 
            on the surface of each individual object in the population./n/nIn 
            simple terms, not only does this number change the width of the 
            population, it also changes the quality./n/nA larger number will 
            help the population to look less jagged, but it comes at a cost of 
            the computer's performance./n/nIf displacement maps are not being 
            used for this population, it is best to set this to a low number (2 
            or 3) since the population is completely flat. Otherwise, raise the 
            number one at a time until either the population looks good enough 
            or the computer starts taking a considerable amount of time to
            generate the population's changes./n/nIf only the population's 
            width needs to be changed (not the quality) it is better to change 
            the width with only the size map if possible.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="populationsVertexHeight">
            <title>How many vertices should make up the height of each 
            individual object</title>
            <text>Choose how many vertices should exist in each column of 
            vertices on the surface of each individual object in the population.
            /n/nIn simple terms, not only does this number change the height of 
            the population, it also changes the quality./n/nA larger number 
            will help the population to look less jagged, but it comes at a 
            cost of the computer's performance./n/nIf displacement maps are not 
            being used for this population, it is best to set this to a low 
            number (2 or 3) since the population is completely flat. Otherwise, 
            raise the number one at a time until either the population looks 
            good enough or the computer begins to take more than a few seconds 
            to generate the population's changes./n/nIf only the population's 
            height needs to be changed (not the quality) it is better to change 
            the height with only the size map if possible.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="populationsDisplacement">
            <title>The range from which the selected population is displaced 
            to</title>
            <text>Choose two color textures that have been imported to create a 
            range of displacement for the population./n/nThese displacement 
            maps function in the same manner as the population's displacement 
            map. The difference is that each vertex belonging to an individual 
            object in the population is moved to a point somewhere between 
            where it would be moved in either of the maps. The purpose of 
            having a range is to allow each object in the population to have a
            somewhat different shape if desired./n/nIf this is difficult to 
            understand, think of one map as being the least of how much the 
            vertices should be positioned, and the other is the most. Each 
            vertex on each object in the population will be positioned based 
            upon a random color between the range of the two maps./n/nTo have 
            each object in the population have the exact same shape, choose the 
            same image for both of the maps.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="populationsStrength">
            <title>The control for setting how much the population should be 
            displaced</title>
            <text>A higher value will make the displacement more extreme, 
            moving the vertices out more. A lower value will make it less 
            noticeable, keeping the vertices closer in.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="populationsDiffuse">
            <title>The diffuse map that the population uses</title>
            <text>Choose a color texture that has been imported to use as a 
            diffuse map. A diffuse map is the actual appearance of the 
            population./n/nA diffuse map can be thought of as being similar to 
            wrapping paper. It does not change the shape of the individual 
            objects in the population at all, but it determines the color and 
            patterns covering the each object in the population.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="populationsBump">
            <title>The bump map that the population uses</title>
            <text>Choose a color texture that has been imported to use as a 
            bump map. A bump map defines the tiny details of the shape of the 
            objects in the population./n/nBump maps technically do not change 
            the shape at all, but rather give the allusion of the shape 
            changing slightly. It is useful for creating details on the surface 
            such as bumps and cracks./n/nSand Paper uses a type of colored bump 
            map known as a normal map. These maps are difficult to create by 
            hand, however, there are applications (such as GIMP) that are 
            capable of applying a filter on the diffuse map to generate a 
            normal map that can be used here.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="populationsSpecular">
            <title>The specular map that the population uses</title>
            <text>Choose a color texture that has been imported to use as a 
            specular map. A specular map determines how much light should be 
            reflected off of each individual object in the population./n/nThe 
            darker parts of the specular map will make the corresponding part 
            of each object in the population to be less reflective, and lighter 
            areas will be more reflective./n/nA specular map is usually created 
            from a grayscale version of the diffuse or bump map. After  
            adjusting the brightness of each area of the image, tints of color 
            can be added to areas of the map to add a tint of color to the 
            reflection.</text>
        </control>
    </group>
    
    <group name="render">
        <control name="renderTab">
            <title>The render tab</title>
            <text>The render tab allows settings to be changed that are related 
            to how a rendered image (a "picture") of the terrain should be 
            created./n/nCreate and save a rendered image by choosing "Save..." 
            or "Save As..." from the File menu.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="renderResolution">
            <title>The resolution for the rendered image when exported</title>
            <text>Set the width and height that the image render of the 
            terrain should be when saved./n/nThe unit of measurement is 
            pixels.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="renderColor">
            <title>The background color selector</title>
            <text>Set the color of the background behind the terrain.</text>
        </control>
    </group>
    
    <group name="camera">
        <control name="cameraTab">
            <title>The camera tab</title>
            <text>The camera tab has settings to adjust how the camera views 
            the terrain./n/nIn 3D modeling, a camera is what controls 
            everything that is currently in view. Just like how a camera 
            in real life can be moved and rotated to change what a picture may 
            look like, so can the virtual camera.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="cameraHorizontal">
            <title>The horizontal camera angle slider</title>
            <text>The angle around the side of the terrain to view it at./n/n0 
            and 360 are the front./n/n90 and 270 are the sides./n/n180 is 
            behind it.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="cameraVertical">
            <title>The vertical camera angle slider</title>
            <text>The angle of how far above the terrain to view it./n/n0 will 
            view the terrain at eye level./n/n90 will view the terrain directly 
            above it.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="cameraX">
            <title>The camera x position adjustment</title>
            <text>Sand Paper always tries to automatically center the view of 
            the terrain. However, sometimes the camera view is not exactly 
            centered, or you may not want it to be centered./n/nIf that is the 
            case, this number can be changed to adjust the camera's x position. 
            A positive number will move the camera that far from the center to 
            the right, while a negative number will move it left. Leaving this 
            number at 0 will put it at what Sand Paper calculates to be the 
            center.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="cameraY">
            <title>The camera y position adjustment</title>
            <text>Sand Paper always tries to automatically center the view of 
            the terrain. However, sometimes the camera view is not exactly 
            centered, or you may not want it to be centered./n/nIf that is the 
            case, this number can be changed to adjust the camera's y position. 
            A positive number will move the camera that far below the center, 
            while a negative number will move it above. Leaving this number at 
            0 will put it at what Sand Paper calculates to be the center.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="cameraZ">
            <title>The camera z position adjustment</title>
            <text>Sand Paper always tries to automatically center the view of 
            the terrain. However, sometimes the camera view is not exactly 
            centered, or you may not want it to be centered./n/nIf that is the 
            case, this number can be changed to adjust the camera's z position. 
            A positive number will move the camera that far forward, while a 
            negative number will move it backward. Leaving this number at 0 
            will put it at what Sand Paper calculates to be the center.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="fieldOfViewDegrees">
            <title>The slider for the field of view</title>
            <text>The virtual "lens angle" of the camera./n/nSetting it to a 
            larger number will have a "wide angle lens" effect, causing more on 
            the sides of the camera to be seen, but it may distort the view. A 
            smaller number will make less to be in view and may make the 
            terrain have a flat look to it.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="fieldOfViewOrientation">
            <title>The orientation radio buttons for the field of view</title>
            <text>The orientation to which the field of view is to be based off 
            of.</text>
        </control>
    </group>
    
    <group name="lights">
        <control name="lightsTab">
            <title>The lights tab</title>
            <text>The lights tab can be used to create and edit lights around 
            the terrain./n/nIn 3D modeling, a light is a specific spot that 
            emitts virtual light to everything around. These can be used to 
            change how bright or dark certain areas of the terrain can 
            be.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="lightsChosen">
            <title>The light selection box</title>
            <text>Select a light to edit in this box. Any changes made to the 
            settings on this tab will apply only to the light selected in this 
            box.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="lightsNew">
            <title>The new light button</title>
            <text>Creates a new light./n/nYou will get to give the light a 
            name. The light will then be selectable in the combo box directly 
            above this button.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="lightsDelete">
            <title>The delete light button</title>
            <text>Deletes the light that is currently selected.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="lightsX">
            <title>The light's x position</title>
            <text>The x position of the light that is currently selected./n/n
            Lights in Sand Paper are positioned with a percentage used as a 
            unit of measurement./n/n0% will place the light on the left edge of 
            the terrain./n100% will place it at the right edge./n50% will put 
            it at the center./nAnything less than 0% will place it to the left 
            of the terrain, and anything more than 100% will place it to the 
            right of the terrain.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="lightsY">
            <title>The light's y position</title>
            <text>The y position of the light that is currently selected./n/n
            Lights in Sand Paper are positioned with a percentage used as a 
            unit of measurement./n/n0% will place the light above the terrain 
            with a distance of about half of the terrain's size./n100% will 
            place the light below the terrain with a distance of about half of 
            the terrain's size./n50% will put the light on the surface of the 
            terrain./nAnything less than 0% will place it further below the 
            terrain than half of the terrain's size, and anything more than 
            100% will place it further above the terrain than half of the 
            terrain's size.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="lightsZ">
            <title>The light's z position</title>
            <text>The z position of the light that is currently selected./n/n
            Lights in Sand Paper are positioned with a percentage used as a 
            unit of measurement./n/n0% will place the light at the back edge of 
            the terrain./n100% will place the light at the front edge of the 
            terrain./n50% will put the light at the terrain center./nAnything 
            less than 0% will place it behind the terrain, and anything more than 
            100% will place it in front of the terrain.</text>
        </control>
        <control name="lightsColor">
            <title>The light color selector</title>
            <text>The color of the light that is currently selected./n/n 
            Choosing a darker color will cause the light to be less intense, 
            whereas a brighter color will make it more intense.</text>
        </control>
    </group>
</root>
